{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The behaviour of visco-elastic material is time dependent. This behaviour is common in __________ materials.", "opta": "non-crystalline solid", "optb": "crystalline", "optc": "rubberry", "optd": "non-crystalline organic polymeric.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coke oven regenerators are made of __________ bricks.", "opta": "fire clay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "low thermal conductivity", "optd": "high electrical conductivity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is universally employed as the low expansion metal in the bimetallic thermometer, which is an iron-nickel alloy containing 36% nickel and has very low co-efficient of expansion (l/20th of ordinary metals) ?", "opta": "Invar", "optb": "Constantan", "optc": "Chromel", "optd": "Alumel", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shock resisting steels should possess high", "opta": "hardness", "optb": "toughness", "optc": "tensile strength", "optd": "wear resistance", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The purpose of nitriding the steel is to", "opta": "harden its surface.", "optb": "soften its surface.", "optc": "improve its reliability.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic recuperators are generally made of", "opta": "silicon carbide.", "optb": "calcium carbide.", "optc": "fireclay bricks.", "optd": "high alumina bricks.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hammers and railway rails are normally made of", "opta": "mild steel", "optb": "dead mild steel", "optc": "medium carbon steel", "optd": "high carbon steel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Softness of silver can be converted into hardness by alloying it with small quantity of", "opta": "copper & nickel", "optb": "zinc", "optc": "aluminium", "optd": "tin", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The addition of antimony in tin-based alloys improves its", "opta": "rupture strength and hot hardness.", "optb": "impact strength and bonding strength.", "optc": "deformation resistance.", "optd": "wear resistance.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The melleability of a material is the property by virtue of which it can be rolled or hammered into thin sheets. Which of the following materials has the miximum malleability ?", "opta": "Lead", "optb": "Copper", "optc": "Aluminium", "optd": "Wrought iron", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main purpose of galvanising iron sheets is to", "opta": "harden the surface.", "optb": "increase its glossiness and lustre.", "optc": "prevent the action of water.", "optd": "prevent the action of oxygen.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The impure iron (pig iron) that is tapped out from blast furnace contains about __________ percent carbon.", "opta": "0.2", "optb": "2", "optc": "4", "optd": "8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Invar used in thermocouples is an alloy of nickel and", "opta": "iron", "optb": "copper", "optc": "chromium", "optd": "lead", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nickel (56%) and molybdenum (17%) alloys are called", "opta": "monel", "optb": "hastealloy C", "optc": "inconel", "optd": "bronzes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lead pipes are not safe for carrying drinking water because water containing dissolved oxygen attacks lead thereby forming poisonous Pb (OH)2. Lead pipes are readily corroded by", "opta": "dilute HCI", "optb": "acetic acid", "optc": "concentrated H2SO4", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Constituents of stellite are", "opta": "zinc, copper and nickel.", "optb": "cobalt, chromium and tungsten.", "optc": "zinc, aluminium and nickel.", "optd": "nickel, cobalt and vanadium.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Residual magnetism in steel for magnets is increased by the addition of", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "cobalt", "optc": "tungsten", "optd": "chromium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of nickel in steel improves its", "opta": "corrosion resistance.", "optb": "cutting ability.", "optc": "wear resistance.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cementite is", "opta": "Fe3C chemically.", "optb": "a compound of carbon and iron.", "optc": "characterised by an orthorhombic crystal structure.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acetylene gas holder is made of", "opta": "copper", "optb": "cast iron", "optc": "steel", "optd": "monel metal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sulphur melting pit in the sulphuric acid plant is made of", "opta": "lead lined stainless steel.", "optb": "cast iron.", "optc": "steel or cement-brick lined.", "optd": "hard wood.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardest material just prior to diamond in Mho's scale is", "opta": "topax", "optb": "carborundum", "optc": "corrundum", "optd": "calcite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Percentage elongation of a material is a measure of its", "opta": "ductility", "optb": "brittleness", "optc": "toughness", "optd": "malleability", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chlorination of benzene is done to produce benzene hexachloride (a pesticide) in a photochemical reactor lined with", "opta": "karbate", "optb": "lead or glass", "optc": "fireclay bricks", "optd": "PVC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heavy duty bearings are usually made of", "opta": "white metal", "optb": "phosphorous bronze", "optc": "monel", "optd": "zinc", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dielectric strength of a material is", "opta": "its energy stroage capacity.", "optb": "a magnetic property.", "optc": "its capacity to resist the flow of current.", "optd": "its capacity to withstand high voltage.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following stainless steels is non-magnetic ?", "opta": "Ferritic", "optb": "Martensitic", "optc": "Austenitic", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "18-4-1 high speed steel contains 18%, 4% and 1% respectively of", "opta": "tungsten, vanadium and chromium", "optb": "tungsten, chromium and vanadium", "optc": "vanadium, chromium and tungsten", "optd": "chromium, tungsten and vanadium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aluminium as a material of construction suffers from the disadvantage of", "opta": "very high cost.", "optb": "rather low tensile strength.", "optc": "very low strength to weight ratio.", "optd": "scarce availability.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Babbit metal used for bearings is a____base alloy.", "opta": "tin", "optb": "lead", "optc": "aluminium", "optd": "copper", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "18/8 steel is a/an __________ stainless steel.", "opta": "austenitic", "optb": "ferritic", "optc": "martensitic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast iron has very high", "opta": "compressive strength", "optb": "ductility", "optc": "shock resistance", "optd": "resistance to brittleness", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Liquid ammonia is shipped in __________ containers.", "opta": "steel", "optb": "aluminium", "optc": "glass", "optd": "lead lined", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cermets are __________ materials.", "opta": "refractory", "optb": "reinforced", "optc": "abrasive", "optd": "fully metallic", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast irons are generally specified by their", "opta": "carbon content", "optb": "tensile strength", "optc": "hardness", "optd": "manufacturing proces", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Austenitic manganese steel used for making jaws of crushing machines contains about __________ percent manganese.", "opta": "1.5-2", "optb": "3.5-4.5", "optc": "7-9", "optd": "12-14", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "White cast iron is not", "opta": "malleable", "optb": "whitish in color", "optc": "brittle", "optd": "strong and hard", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Galvanised iron is", "opta": "harder", "optb": "protected from rusting", "optc": "alumina coated iron", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "German silver used for decorative purposes contains maximum percentage of", "opta": "silver", "optb": "copper", "optc": "zinc", "optd": "nickel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The metals occuring at the lower most position in the electromotive series", "opta": "do not resist corrosion.", "optb": "resist corrosion very strongly.", "optc": "are very brittle.", "optd": "are heat insulators.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "German silver in an alloy of", "opta": "copper, nickel and zinc.", "optb": "copper, aluminium and silver.", "optc": "silver, zinc and aluminium.", "optd": "silver, nickel and zinc.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A suitable material of construction to use with fuming sulphuric acid is", "opta": "carbon steel", "optb": "stainless steel type 304", "optc": "nickel", "optd": "monel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following crystal structures characterises the austenitic stainless steel?", "opta": "Simple hexagonal", "optb": "Body centred cubic", "optc": "Face centred cubic", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Caustic soda is produced in a mercury cell having anode and cathode made respectively of moving mercury and", "opta": "moving mercury and graphite.", "optb": "graphite and moving mercury.", "optc": "moving mercury and carbon.", "optd": "moving mercury and crimped steel wire.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Addition of __________ in steel can help in increasing the depth of hardness.", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "chromium", "optc": "vanadium", "optd": "tungsten", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has the highest compressive strength ?", "opta": "Wrought iron", "optb": "Cast iron", "optc": "Mild steel", "optd": "High carbon steel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zinc is not used", "opta": "for producing zinc base die casting alloys.", "optb": "in its oxide form as pigments.", "optc": "as anode for corrosion prevention in boiler.", "optd": "as an alloying element in various bronzes.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refined acetic acid storage vessel are made of", "opta": "copper", "optb": "aluminium", "optc": "high carbon steel", "optd": "nickel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Addition of __________ to the steel helps in increasing the residual magnetism in steel used for making magnets.", "opta": "chromium", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "tungsten", "optd": "cobalt", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Constantan is an alloy of", "opta": "Cu (55%) & Sn (45%).", "optb": "Cu (55%) & Ni (45%).", "optc": "Pt (95%) & Rh (10%).", "optd": "Fe (80%) & Ni (20%).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}